We once again look
at our game level rendering.
And this time we're going to use a
datatype instead of an Integer encoding
to encode what tiles are placed at what position.
We have this datatype here, called Tile, and it
has the constructors Block, Water, Pearl, and Air.
And now I've copied the
level from Task 11 in here.
Still with the integer encoding.
And now we're going to change
it to use this datatype.
And because we don't have a value
in this type for a position where
there's no tile, we use Maybe Tile as
the result type of the level function.
And we use Nothing as described above here
in the same way we used 0 before,
for when there is actually no tile.
So when this function returns Nothing, there
actually is nothing there to be drawn.
Okay, so let's start with this.
So as I said, 0 becomes Nothing in this
case, which is outside of the level.
Then 1 was the number for a block
tile, and we just say, okay,
this is Just the Block value; same here.
Water was 2, now um it's Just Water.
And you can see it's far more descriptive
if we use a datatype instead of this
Integer encoding where we had to write
next to it what it should represent.
And it's way easier to get it right this way.
So 3 is a Pearl;
same here.
And 4 is Just Air.
Okay, so now we also got rid of this red
squiggly line telling us that it was a type error
because we were giving back Integer numbers
but said it would be values of Maybe Tile.
Now it's values of Maybe
Tile; everything is good.
Okay then, these values; how
to actually draw these tiles
don't change because they are not depending on
this datatype but our function that converts
a Tile into a Picture
- one of these values -
obviously now is different than
when we gave it integers as input.
So, we're going to do pattern
matching on these four constructors.
So we have a Block value,
then we use the block image.
If we have the Water value, it's the water
image and so on, pretty straightforward.
And the last one for Air
is just the picture of air.
Okay, so notice that we don't have a value
in this function for Nothing as we had with 0
in the integer encoding where we said
everything that's not the above, or maybe we
actually matched explicitly on 0 too, is blank.
This is not the case here since this
datatype just describes all the possible tiles
and not the possibility for there being nothing.
That is encoded in this Maybe, and
we'll have to handle it at another point
namely in this visualize function.
And we'll do so in a second.
Okay, so now this visualize function should
do the same thing as in the previous task.
You should visualize the level in the range of
-10 to 10, but this time around we should not
use recursion or list comprehensions,
but we can still use these ranges.
Okay, so we know that list
comprehensions can be expressed with
map, concat, and filter by
combining them in the right way.
Map seems like a good place to start
so let's map something over [-10..10]
because that's probably where we
want our values to be drawn from.
Let's call them x and now we
have x values from -10 to 10.
Let's do another map because that's how we
translate this list comprehensions
to map and filter and concat.
We just nest these maps together,
and in the end, we will concat
the list back to its original depth, so to speak.
So using this map here over the same range since
the y values will also be drawn from this range
we built this inner function.
And now we can do something with
x and y which are all coordinates.
And what we want to do is we want
to draw the tile at this position.
Okay, let's leave this blank for the
moment for what this drawTile should be.
Let's just put undefined there and make sure
we get the type right for this expression.
So we used map and nested inside it another map
so this will result in a list of whatever we do
with drawTiles and this list that we produce
here is one element of the outside list.
So we have a list of lists here.
And when we look at this, it says that the
actual type is a list of lists of something
and it matches this with the actual type
which is at this point a function type
because we haven't given the level a name.
So now it says it can't match Picture with
the type list of lists of some values,
it doesn't know yet.
Okay, so we want to go to a Picture from probably
a list of lists of Pictures if we think about it.
drawTile should probably give us a Picture.
Since list comprehensions are made
out of these 'map' and 'filter'
and 'concat' applications, we could just
use concat to concat the whole list down.
And now we have that Picture can't
be matched with a list of somethings,
which probably will be Pictures.
So let's just say we call 'pictures' on this just
like we did in the list comprehension version.
And now this infers that drawTile should
do something that results in a Picture.
Okay, something we can do here is we
can, instead of doing concat and map
separately, use a function called concatMap
that saves us one set of parentheses.
Makes it more clear what we are doing here.
Okay, so for readability we've
separated out this drawTile thing.
And drawTile now, for some integer
values x and y, what do we do for this?
Well, we had this 'translated' by x and y
in the original solution, because we have to move
each tile to the place where it should be placed.
And then we would use
the aTile function on the level, which we
called aLevel, at x and y returned us. Okay.
Now we get an error here regarding the Maybe.
We'll fix that in a second.
Since we have as always the problem that
"translated" takes Double parameters and we are
only at Integer values, we need to use fromIntegral
here and now aLevel returns a value of Maybe Tile.
But aTile takes a value of type Tile.
Okay, so um how do we do this?
Well, let's define another function drawMaybe
that takes a value that is maybe a
Tile; could be Nothing or Just the tile.
And let's check with the help of the functions
we imported from Data.Maybe if it is Just ...
If this Maybe Tile value is Just, then we can use
fromJust and do aTile of fromJust on our value.
Which gives us our picture.
If this is not the case, meaning we have Nothing
here, then we just say that's the blank image.
And now instead of doing this
here, we can just say drawMaybe.
And this aLevel now takes the coordinates and
turns them into a Maybe Tile value, and
this drawMaybe takes care of unpacking this
Maybe value and either drawing the tile or a
blank image if there's no tile to be drawn.
There are a couple of other
ways how we can do this.
There are some higher-order ways to do this.
You could also use pattern-matching, but
for now, let's stick with this version
which is quite straightforward and
easy to follow without too much
additional syntactic elements.
Okay, let's see if it actually works.
This looks like our level.
Like we would imagine, good.
We could now change this level,
maybe use something different
to visualize here, but this works fine.
And the principle is the same no matter
what level you choose, obviously.
Okay, that's that for this task.